<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-kowalik-rpp-data-objects-00" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" indexInclude="true" tocDepth="4">

<front>
<title abbrev="RPP Data Objects">Registry Provisioning Protocol (RPP) Data Objects</title><seriesInfo value="draft-kowalik-rpp-data-objects-00" stream="IETF" status="standard" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="P." surname="Kowalik" fullname="Pawel Kowalik"><organization>DENIC</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>pawel.kowalik@denic.de</email>
<uri>https://denic.de/</uri>
</address></author><date/>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>This document defines abstract data objects for the Registry
Provisioning Protocol (RPP). The definitions for domain name,
contact, and host objects focus on the logical structure and
constraints of their constituent data elements, independent of any
specific data representation or media type. This document follows the
architecture defined in [I-D.kowalik-rpp-architecture].</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t>The Registry Provisioning Protocol (RPP) requires a clear definition of its data objects. This document catalogues the fundamental resource objects managed through RPP: domains, contacts, and hosts.</t>
<t>In accordance with the RPP architecture <xref target="I-D.kowalik-rpp-architecture"></xref>, the definitions herein are abstract. They specify the logical data elements, their meanings, and their constraints, rather than a specific representation format. This approach ensures that the core data model can be consistently implemented across different media types.</t>

<section anchor="conventions-and-terminology"><name>Conventions and Terminology</name>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="resource-definition-principles"><name>Resource Definition Principles</name>

<section anchor="data-element-abstraction"><name>Data Element Abstraction</name>
<t>Each resource is composed of logical data elements. A data element is a logical unit of information identified by a stable name, independent of its representation in any given media type. The definition for each element specifies its logical name, purpose, cardinality, data type, and constraints.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="extensibility"><name>Extensibility</name>
<t>The set of data elements for a given resource object is extensible. New data elements MAY be defined and registered with IANA to support new features.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="data-element-semantics"><name>Data Element Semantics</name>
<t>The definition of each data element within an object consists of the
following attributes:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Name: A human-readable name for the data element.</li>
<li>Identifier: A machine-readable, unique identifier for the element, using camelCase notation.</li>
<li><t>Cardinality: Specifies the number of times an element may appear. The notation is as follows:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><tt>1</tt> for exactly one</li>
<li><tt>0-1</tt> for zero or one</li>
<li><tt>0+</tt> for zero or more</li>
<li>and <tt>1+</tt> for one or more</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Type: Defines the element's data structure, which can be a primitive type (e.g., String, Integer) or a reference to another component object.</li>
<li>Description: Explains the purpose of the data element and any other relevant information.</li>
<li>Constraints: Provides specific validation rules or limitations on top of the data type itself, such as value ranges.</li>
<li><t>Mutability: Defines the lifecycle of the data element's value. It MUST be one of the following:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>create-only: The element's value is provided during the object's creation and cannot be modified thereafter.</li>
<li>read-only: The element's value is managed by the server. It cannot be set or modified directly by the client, though it may change as a result of server-side operations.</li>
<li>read-write: The element's value can be set and modified by the client.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="common-data-types"><name>Common Data Types</name>
<t>This section defines primitive data types and structures that are re-
used across multiple resource object definitions.</t>

<section anchor="identifiers"><name>Identifiers</name>
<t>(Definition of a common type for identifiers, e.g., for contacts or hosts)</t>
</section>

<section anchor="timestamps"><name>Timestamps</name>
<t>(Definition of a standardized timestamp format, e.g., ISO 8601)</t>
</section>

<section anchor="status-types"><name>Status Types</name>
<t>(Definition of a common structure for status flags on objects)</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="component-objects"><name>Component Objects</name>
<t>This section defines common component objects that are re-used in the definitions of top-level resource objects.</t>

<section anchor="period-object"><name>Period Object</name>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Name: Period Object</li>
<li>Identifier: period</li>
<li>Description: Represents a duration of time.</li>
<li><t>Data Elements:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><t>Value</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: value</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: Integer.</li>
<li>Description: The numeric value of the period.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be from 1 to 99, inclusive.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Unit</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: unit</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Token).</li>
<li>Description: The unit of the period.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be one of: &quot;y&quot; (years) or &quot;m&quot; (months).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="nameserver-object"><name>Nameserver Object</name>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Name: Nameserver Object</li>
<li>Identifier: nameserver</li>
<li>Description: Represents a single nameserver.</li>
<li><t>Data Elements:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><t>Host Name</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: hostName</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: String.</li>
<li>Description: The name of the host.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be a syntactically valid host name.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>IP Addresses</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: ipAddresses</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0+</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: String.</li>
<li>Description: IP addresses associated with the host.</li>
<li>Constraints: Each value MUST be a syntactically valid IPv4 or IPv6 address.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="contact-association-object"><name>Contact Association Object</name>

<aside><t>TODO: find a better name for Identifier</t>
<t>TODO: decide if association with attributes shouldn't be something else</t>
</aside>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Name: Contact Association Object</li>
<li>Identifier: contactAssociation</li>
<li>Description: Links a Contact resource to another resource, defining the role of the association.</li>
<li><t>Data Elements:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><t>Identifier</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: identifier</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Client Identifier).</li>
<li>Description: The identifier of the associated contact object.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be a valid, server-known Client Identifier.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Type</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: type</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Token).</li>
<li>Description: The role of the associated contact.</li>
<li>Constraints: For domain name associations, the value MUST be one of: &quot;admin&quot;, &quot;billing&quot;, or &quot;tech&quot;.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="authorization-information-object"><name>Authorization Information Object</name>

<aside><t>TODO: define it better</t>
</aside>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Name: Authorization Information Object</li>
<li>Identifier: authInfo</li>
<li>Description: Contains information used to authorize operations on a resource object.</li>
<li>Data Elements: The structure of this object is intentionally left abstract to accommodate various authentication mechanisms (e.g., password, token). The server defines the specific elements and constraints.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="domain-name-resource-object"><name>Domain Name Resource Object</name>

<section anchor="object-description"><name>Object Description</name>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Name: Domain Name Resource Object</li>
<li>Identifier: domainName</li>
<li>Description: A Domain Name resource object represents a domain name and contains the data required for its provisioning and management in the registry.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="data-elements"><name>Data Elements</name>
<t>The following data elements are defined for the Domain Name resource object.</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Name</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: name</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: create-only</li>
<li>Data Type: String.</li>
<li>Description: The fully qualified name of the domain object.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be a fully qualified domain name that conforms to the syntax described in <xref target="RFC1035"></xref>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Repository ID</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: repositoryId</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: String.</li>
<li>Description: A server-assigned unique identifier for the object.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Status</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: status</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0+</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Token).</li>
<li>Description: The current status descriptors associated with the domain.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be one of the status tokens defined in the IANA registry for domain statuses.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Registrant</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: registrant</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Client Identifier).</li>
<li>Description: The contact object associated with the domain as the registrant.</li>
<li>Constraints: The identifier MUST correspond to a valid Contact resource object known to the server.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Contacts</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: contacts</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0+</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: A collection of Contact Association Objects.</li>
<li>Description: A collection of other contact objects associated with the domain object.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Nameservers</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: nameservers</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: A collection of Nameserver Objects.</li>
<li>Description: A collection of nameservers associated with the domain.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Subordinate Hosts</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: subordinateHosts</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0+</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: Collection of Strings.</li>
<li>Description: A collection of fully qualified names of subordinate host objects that exist under this domain.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Sponsoring Client ID</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: sponsoringClientId</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Client Identifier).</li>
<li>Description: The identifier of the client that is the current sponsor of the domain object.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Creating Client ID</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: creatingClientId</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Client Identifier).</li>
<li>Description: The identifier of the client that created the domain object.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Creation Date</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: creationDate</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: Timestamp.</li>
<li>Description: The date and time of domain object creation.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value is set by the server and cannot be specified by the client.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Updating Client ID</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: updatingClientId</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Client Identifier).</li>
<li>Description: The identifier of the client that last updated the domain object.</li>
<li>Constraints: This element MUST NOT be present if the domain has never been modified.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Update Date</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: updateDate</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: Timestamp.</li>
<li>Description: The date and time of the most recent domain object modification.</li>
<li>Constraints: This element MUST NOT be present if the domain object has never been modified.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Expiry Date</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: expiryDate</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: Timestamp.</li>
<li>Description: The date and time identifying the end of the domain object's registration period.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value is set by the server and cannot be specified by the client.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Transfer Date</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: transferDate</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-only</li>
<li>Data Type: Timestamp.</li>
<li>Description: The date and time of the most recent successful domain object transfer.</li>
<li>Constraints: This element MUST NOT be provided if the domain object has never been transferred.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Authorization Information</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: authInfo</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Mutability: read-write</li>
<li>Data Type: Authorization Information Object.</li>
<li>Description: Authorization information to be associated with the domain object.</li>
<li>Constraints: (None)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="operations"><name>Operations</name>

<section anchor="create-operation"><name>Create Operation</name>
<t>The Create operation allows a client to provision a new Domain Name resource. The operation accepts as input all create-only and read-write data elements defined for the Domain Name Resource Object.</t>
<t>In addition, the following transient data element is defined for this operation:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li><t>Registration Period</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: period</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Data Type: Period Object.</li>
<li>Description: The initial registration period for the domain name. This value is used by the server to calculate the initial <tt>expiryDate</tt> of the object. This element is not persisted as part of the object's state.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="read-operation"><name>Read Operation</name>
<t>The Read operation allows a client to retrieve the data elements of a
Domain Name resource. The server's response MAY vary depending on
client authorization and server policy.</t>
<t>The following transient data elements are defined for this operation:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Hosts Filter</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: hostsFilter</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Data Type: String (Token).</li>
<li>Description: Controls which host information is returned with
the object.</li>
<li>Constraints: The value MUST be one of &quot;all&quot;, &quot;del&quot;
(delegated), &quot;sub&quot; (subordinate), or &quot;none&quot;. The default value
is &quot;all&quot;.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Query Authorization Information</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: queryAuthInfo</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Data Type: Authorization Information Object.</li>
<li>Description: Authorization information provided by the client
to gain access to the full set of the object's data elements.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="delete-operation"><name>Delete Operation</name>
<t>The Delete operation allows a client to remove an existing Domain
Name resource. The operation targets a specific resource object
identified by its name.</t>
<t>The server SHOULD reject a delete request if subordinate host objects
are associated with the domain name.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="renew-operation"><name>Renew Operation</name>
<t>The Renew operation allows a client to extend the validity period of
an existing Domain Name resource. The operation targets a specific
resource object identified by its name.</t>
<t>The following transient data elements are defined for this operation:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Current Expiry Date</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: currentExpiryDate</li>
<li>Cardinality: 1</li>
<li>Data Type: Timestamp</li>
<li>Description: The current expiry date of the domain name. The
server MUST validate this against the object's current
<tt>expiryDate</tt> to prevent unintended duplicate renewals.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Renewal Period</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Identifier: renewalPeriod</li>
<li>Cardinality: 0-1</li>
<li>Data Type: Period Object</li>
<li>Description: The duration to be added to the object's
registration period. This value is used by the server to
calculate the new <tt>expiryDate</tt>.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<t>Contact Resource Object</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="object-description-1"><name>Object Description</name>
<t>A Contact resource object represents the social information for an
individual or organization associated with other objects.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="data-elements-1"><name>Data Elements</name>
<t>(This section will list and define the abstract data elements for a
contact.)</t>
<t>Host Resource Object</t>
</section>

<section anchor="object-description-2"><name>Object Description</name>
<t>A Host resource object represents a name server that provides DNS
services for a a domain name.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="data-elements-2"><name>Data Elements</name>
<t>(This section will list and define the abstract data elements for a
host.)</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>

<section anchor="rpp-object-registry"><name>RPP Object Registry</name>
<t>This document establishes the &quot;Registry Provisioning Protocol (RPP)
Object Registry&quot;. This registry serves as a definitive, hierarchical
catalogue of all resource objects, component objects, data elements,
and operations used within RPP.</t>

<section anchor="registration-policy"><name>Registration Policy</name>
<t>The policy for adding new objects, data elements, or operations to
this registry is &quot;Specification Required&quot; <xref target="RFC8126"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-structure"><name>Registry Structure</name>
<t>The registry is organized as a collection of Object definitions. Each
Object definition MUST include:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>A header containing the Object Identifier, Object Name, Object
Type (Resource or Component), a brief description, and a
reference to its defining specification.</t>
</li>
<li><t>A &quot;Data Elements&quot; table listing all persisted data elements
associated with the object. Each entry MUST specify the element's
Identifier, Name, Cardinality, Mutability, Data Type, and
description.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If applicable, an &quot;Operations&quot; section. For each operation, the
registry MUST provide:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>The Operation's Name and a description.</li>
<li>A &quot;Parameters&quot; table listing all data elements that
are provided as input to the operation but are not persisted
as part of the object's state. Each entry MUST specify the
parameter's Identifier, Name, Cardinality, Data Type, and a
description.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="initial-registrations"><name>Initial Registrations</name>
<t>The initial contents of the RPP Object Registry are defined below.</t>
<t>Object: period</t>
<t>Object Name: Period Object</t>
<t>Object Type: Component</t>
<t>Description: Represents a duration of time.</t>
<t>Reference: [This-ID]</t>
<t>Data Elements</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Element Identifier</th>
<th>Element Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Mutability</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>value</td>
<td>Value</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>Integer</td>
<td>The numeric value of the period.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>unit</td>
<td>Unit</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>Token</td>
<td>The unit of the period.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Object: nameserver</t>
<t>Object Name: Nameserver Object</t>
<t>Object Type: Component</t>
<t>Description: Represents a single nameserver.</t>
<t>Reference: [This-ID]</t>
<t>Data Elements</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Element Identifier</th>
<th>Element Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Mutability</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>hostName</td>
<td>Host Name</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>String</td>
<td>The name of the host.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>ipAddresses</td>
<td>IP Addresses</td>
<td>0+</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>String</td>
<td>IP addresses associated with the host.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Object: contactAssociation</t>
<t>Object Name: Contact Association Object</t>
<t>Object Type: Component</t>
<t>Description: Links a Contact resource to another resource, defining its role.</t>
<t>Reference: [This-ID]</t>
<t>Data Elements</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Element Identifier</th>
<th>Element Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Mutability</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>identifier</td>
<td>Identifier</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>String (Client ID)</td>
<td>The identifier of the associated contact object.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>type</td>
<td>Type</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>Token</td>
<td>The role of the associated contact.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Object: authInfo</t>
<t>Object Name: Authorization Information Object</t>
<t>Object Type: Component</t>
<t>Description: Contains authorization credentials for an operation.</t>
<t>Reference: [This-ID]</t>
<t>Data Elements</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Element Identifier</th>
<th>Element Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Mutability</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>(n/a)</td>
<td>Authorization Info</td>
<td>(n/a)</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>Abstract Object</td>
<td>Authentication credentials.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Object: domainName</t>
<t>Object Name: Domain Name Resource Object</t>
<t>Object Type: Resource</t>
<t>Description: Represents a domain name and its associated data.</t>
<t>Reference: [This-ID]</t>
<t>Data Elements</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Identifier</th>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Mutability</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>name</td>
<td>Name</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>create-only</td>
<td>String</td>
<td>The fully qualified name of the domain object.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>repositoryId</td>
<td>Repository ID</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>String</td>
<td>A server-assigned unique identifier for the object.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>status</td>
<td>Status</td>
<td>0+</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>Token</td>
<td>The current status descriptors for the domain.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>registrant</td>
<td>Registrant</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>String (Client ID)</td>
<td>The registrant contact ID.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>contacts</td>
<td>Contacts</td>
<td>0+</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>Collection (contactAssociation)</td>
<td>Associated contact objects.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>nameservers</td>
<td>Nameservers</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>Collection (nameserver)</td>
<td>Associated nameserver objects.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>subordinateHosts</td>
<td>Subordinate Hosts</td>
<td>0+</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>Collection (String)</td>
<td>Subordinate host names.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>sponsoringClientId</td>
<td>Sponsoring Client ID</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>String (Client ID)</td>
<td>The current sponsoring client ID.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>creatingClientId</td>
<td>Creating Client ID</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>String (Client ID)</td>
<td>The client ID that created the object.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>creationDate</td>
<td>Creation Date</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>Timestamp</td>
<td>Creation timestamp.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>updatingClientId</td>
<td>Updating Client ID</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>String (Client ID)</td>
<td>The client ID that last updated the object.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>updateDate</td>
<td>Update Date</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>Timestamp</td>
<td>The timestamp of the last update.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>expiryDate</td>
<td>Expiry Date</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>Timestamp</td>
<td>Expiry timestamp.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>transferDate</td>
<td>Transfer Date</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-only</td>
<td>Timestamp</td>
<td>The timestamp of the last successful transfer.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>authInfo</td>
<td>Authorization Info</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>read-write</td>
<td>authInfo</td>
<td>Authorization information for the object.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Operations</t>
<t>Operation: Create</t>
<t>Description: Provisions a new Domain Name resource.</t>
<t>Parameters</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Identifier</th>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>period</td>
<td>Registration Period</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>period</td>
<td>The initial registration period for the domain name.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Operation: Read</t>
<t>Description: Retrieves the data elements of a Domain Name resource.</t>
<t>Parameters</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Identifier</th>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>hostsFilter</td>
<td>Hosts Filter</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>Token</td>
<td>Controls which host information is returned.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>queryAuthInfo</td>
<td>Query Authorization Information</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>authInfo</td>
<td>Credentials to authorize access to full object data.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Operation: Delete</t>
<t>Description: Removes an existing Domain Name resource.</t>
<t>Parameters: (None)</t>
<t>Operation: Renew</t>
<t>Description: Extends the validity period of a Domain Name resource.</t>
<t>Parameters</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Identifier</th>
<th>Name</th>
<th>Card.</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>currentExpiryDate</td>
<td>Current Expiry Date</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>Timestamp</td>
<td>The expected current expiry date, for validation.</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>renewalPeriod</td>
<td>Renewal Period</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>period</td>
<td>The duration to add to the registration period.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>Security Considerations</t>
<t>(This section will discuss security issues related to the data
objects, such as data privacy, validation, and potential for misuse.)</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.kowalik-rpp-architecture.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
